[Music]
the heart hi there my name is Andrew
Sweeney welcome to my podcast this is
the third in a series of articles I've
written about Jordan Peterson and for
his various conversation partners and
this is about in McGilchrist who is one
of my favorite writers and he's written
one of the books that I've loved the
most in the last five years so I'm
really happy that they had a discussion
together and apparently they're gonna
have a much longer one soon two of the
best books I've read in the past five
years are the master in his emissary by
Iain McGilchrist and maps of meaning by
Jordan Peterson I was therefore thrilled
that a dialog however short and sweet
has taken place between them these are
men who to use the pop culture term have
read pilled a lot of people are taking
us down a deep rabbit hole of
illumination inversion great beauty and
sometimes sheer terror both men have
done something monumental in my view
that is to say they are peacemakers by
this I mean they have bridged the
disparate warring worlds for instance
phenomenology and science religion and
empiricism poetry and objectivity in
other words they have metaphorically
speaking combined the right brain view
of the world with the left brain view
and Ian McGill crests formulation they
have showed us how a real renaissance or
unification of culture can come into
being by restoring the proper
relationship between the it or the
objective world of tools and concepts
and the vow or the living world of
subjective mystery both McGilchrist and
peterson combined multiple disciplines
to make the bridge from the hard
sciences to the arts psychology and
religion although their descriptions of
the brain hemispheres can't be
elaborated on here without some left
brain reductionism nevertheless we can
generalize about the left-right chaos
order man woman
Academy metaphorically mirrored and then
divided asymmetrical brain as they say
in Zen a finger pointing to the moon is
not the moon itself perhaps to extend
the analogy McGilchrist and Peterson
point from different locations but are
aiming at the same moon to put it
broadly Peterson's mission is to bring
habitable order and coherent meaning to
the world
in other words clean up your room bucko
with Gilcrest on the other hand
criticizes the modern mania for too much
control and arbitrary order while he
acknowledges the necessity of reason and
the scientific method he pushes us
towards the living mystery the right
hemisphere Peterson asks us to make form
out of chaos which seems at least on the
surface to be the function of the left
brain seemingly the opposite approach to
McGilchrist but is there necessarily a
contradiction between these two views or
can we hold them simultaneously
McGilchrist tells us that civilizations
reach their zenith when both hemispheres
metaphorically speaking exist in proper
relationship that means the right brain
view based on depth the body and
intuition is sovereign the right brain
master should rule over the more
instrumental mapping and technocratic
left brain servant Peterson on the other
hand talks about how mythological and
traditional boundaries provide the
proper framework for us to orient
ourselves in a world of suffering and
malevolence how logos are articulated
truth speech creates order from chaos
and frees us from ideological possession
McGill crest argues for fluidity and
metaphor perhaps the feminine and Union
terms
whereas Peterson calls for order and
boundaries a more masculine approach
however it is not true that McGill crest
is against reason only that he
distinguishes it from mere rationality
the left brain rations or reduces things
to bits reason as opposed to rationality
brings us more holistic perspective
which includes the metaphysical and the
religious mere rationality cuts us off
from the right hemisphere and leads to
extreme scientific reductionism and
cultural fragmentation but reason
balanced with intuition connects us to
the whole complex being Peterson is not
as conservative and order obsessed or
left hemisphere oriented as all that
however and writes about the hero's need
to fight dragons in the chaotic
underworld still we can see why he has
attracted people who are looking for
meaning and orientation in their lives
Peterson speaks of a need for a balance
between order and chaos conservatism and
liberalism the masculine and the
feminine perhaps the difference between
the two is that McGilchrist privileges
the right brain as the master I wonder
if Peterson would agree with his thesis
these differences might explain some of
the friendly tensions in their
preliminary discussions Peterson
suggested that it was unusual from a
Gilcrest to privilege the right
hemisphere traditionally the left brain
rules the right hand functions of
tool-making language and generally
making manageable order of chaos
McGilchrist to counter this suggested
that Peterson has leaned too much
towards order and might not acknowledge
the necessary chaos and the richness of
the right hemisphere this may be a
legitimate critique of some of
Peterson's low-resolution ideas which
can at times be overly reductive in the
service of polemical statements this
tension may also have something to do
with the differences in personalities of
the two men McGill crest appears almost
camera-shy he has a tendency towards
melancholy I would say he is very
connected to the bitter sweetness of the
heart to put it poetic Lee he has an
introvert and doesn't appear to cherish
the public eye
whereas Peterson is an obvious extrovert
is combative and seems to have taken to
the public stage with a certain relish
perhaps we could say that Peterson has
an excess of charisma and McGilchrist
an excess of sadness this is not a
critique we need more access in this
conformist society the road of excess
leads to the palace of wisdom as William
Blake is
Peterson has used left brain anger to
cut through the superficialities of the
culture but with deep right brain depth
and feeling for the issues at hand
McGill crest on the other hand has
combined his right brain oriented depths
for music and painting for instance with
the empirical left brain sphere of brain
science and philosophy it should be
added that both men have considerable
clinical experience and after very
practical rather than merely
intellectual observations they are
heroes of a sort they have moved from
the sphere of left brain abstraction to
unity and integration where the master
is no longer a slave to his tools but
uses them wisely their task has been to
bring the shadow puppet to life to move
from the dead matter of mere
conceptuality to the living world of the
spirit
both Peterson and McGilchrist are great
integrity' thinkers which we need at
this moment to heal the wounds of
extreme fragmentation and polarization